[music]
All right. Well, hello. I'm Derek Radney
and I'm a pastor in Winston Salem, North
Carolina at uh Trinity [music] Church
PCA and I'm hosting this conversation
today about the identity and uh the
founding vision of the PCA on behalf of
the Alliance for Mission and Renewal. Uh
the alliance exists to help foster a
unified, faithful, and flourishing PCA.
We are an organization dedicated to
assisting and encouraging churches,
ministry leaders, and all uh PCA sisters
and brothers in the work of
communicating the gospel of Jesus Christ
in our current cult cultural moment. And
we want to tell stories and celebrate
stories about the beautiful ways God is
working in and through our denomination.
My conversation today is with uh the
Reverend Dr. Shawn Michael Lucas who is
an executive board member of A4MR. Um
Dr. Lucas is the senior pastor of
Independent Presbyterian Church in
Memphis, Tennessee. And he is the
chancellor's professor of church history
at Reformed Theological Seminary in
Jackson, Mississippi, I believe. Is that
right, Sean?
>> Sure. Yeah.
>> Okay. Okay.
>> I I teach across the system, but yes.
>> Okay. Okay. Um, he received his PhD from
Westminster Theological Seminary in 2002
and has been ordained in the PCA since
2003, is the author of many books, both
theological and historical, and he is
married to his wife Sarah, and has four
adult children. So, Sean, thank you for
joining me today.
>> Well, thanks for having me, Derek. This
is going to be fun.
>> I'm looking forward to this. Um, we're
going to be discussing the identity and
founding vision of the PCA. And we're
going to do that by focusing on one of
your books that's about the history of
the PCA called uh for a continuing
church. Right here I've got it, the
roots of the Presbyterian Church in
America. Um, and so I kind of want to
set up our conversation a little bit by
talking about one of the challenges that
I'm seeing, at least from my
perspective, going on in our
denomination right now. Uh obviously
there's there's kind of a growing
polarization
uh that in some ways imitates the
polarization of our broader culture. Um
but that that polarization in some ways
seems to be uh related to the fact that
we have different visions of who we are
as a denomination. And thus our history
and founding is a big question for us as
a denomination as we kind of debate who
we're going to be in the future. And I
think this is especially true. This sort
of lack of uh understanding our history
in the guys that are in seminary now are
just coming out of it maybe isn't
limited to them, but it seems like uh a
lot of folks just don't know who we are
and who we have been. And so I could be
wrong about this, but it seems to me
there's two narratives that are playing
out. One is we ha uh we were founded to
be a very uh strict uh uh reformed
denomination um that has just kind of
had this slow slide into a more loose
denomination
and um and kind of encroaching
liberalism. And then the other vision is
we were founded as a a sort of more
broadly reformed evangelical
conservative and mainline denomination
and we've largely stayed that way with
various discussions and battles
throughout our history if anything maybe
becoming more in line with the reformed
tradition on the whole. And so those are
kind of two different trajectories that
people understand our denomination to be
on. So, um, that's kind of my aim is to
help us explore that question today in
in looking at your book and talking with
you. And, uh, so before I get into that,
I just want to ask you maybe a little
bit more about yourself so you can help
people understand your own history in
the PCA. So, maybe you could tell us how
you found your way into the PCA, what
ministries you've had in the PCA and so
forth.
>> Sure. So, um, so my parents came to
Christ when I was 10 years old. Um, we
ended up in a kind of uh Plymouth
Brethren non-denominational Bible church
background through my late elementary,
junior high, senior high um life. Uh, I
professed faith when I was 11 or 12
years old. Um, and towards the end of
high school, my parents pulled me out of
my uh, public school and put me in an
independent Baptist Christian school in
Fairfax, Virginia. Uh, and from there,
um, since my dad was had the mindset
that he was, since he was paying for
college, he would pick where I would go
for college. Uh, I ended up going to
Liberty University for a year and then,
um, because they didn't enforce the
rules at Liberty, I wanted to go where
they enforced the rules, ended up at Bob
Jones University, the fortress of the
faith, uh, there in Greenville, South
Carolina. So, um, so yeah, very much a
kind of a securitous route through kind
of, uh, kind of broader evangelicalism
into fundamentalism.
Uh, and at Bob Jones, I was a pastoral
studies and then, uh, I got my master's
degree in theology and church history.
Uh, and it was it was at Bob Jones that
I really became very interested in, uh,
the history of American Christianity.
Um, and uh, also at Bob Jones where I
actually came to the doctrines of grace.
Um, through my systematic theology
classes and my Bible classes, I had uh,
I think six different classes with Mike
Barrett uh, who is now the dean at
Puritan Reformed Theological Seminary up
in Grand Rapids. Uh, and so, um,
graduated with my master's degree, uh,
as a five-point Calvinist and trying to
figure out where to go to do my PhD, uh,
and, uh, ended up going to Westminster
Theological Seminary. Um when we went to
Westminster after Sarah and I got
married in 94, um I was still baptistic,
uh but I I wanted to be Presbyterian and
was very much kind of trying to
understand
um lots of different aspects of the
Presbyterian story. Um so my main
teacher was Daryl Hart, DG Hart, the not
noted American religious historian. I
took nine seminars with Daryl and um
made a humongous impact on my life. uh
my intellectual historical vision very
much shaped uh through his influence. I
I owe him an inestimable debt. Um he was
the one who kind of steered me away from
my intended Jonathan Edwards
dissertation towards uh what I ended up
doing which is I wrote my my
dissertation on Robert Lewis Dabney's
public theology uh and explored kind of
identity theological identity and public
theology uh in u the 19th century south
uh and it was working on Dabney um and
wrestling with infant baptism uh as my
as we kept having children. Uh that
actually got me into the PCA.
Uh by this time we were in Louisville,
Kentucky. I was actually working for
Southern Baptist Theological Seminary.
Crazy story that I've told in other
places. Uh but we ended up in the PCA in
uh 2002. Uh and then uh the church we
were at in Louisville uh called me to be
a part-time assistant pastor. Uh and uh
that's how I was then. That was my
ordainable call. and through kind of a
series of events ended up going to teach
at Covenant Theological Seminary, uh
working as an assistant pastor at
Covenant Presbyterian Church in St.
Louis. Uh and then, uh the last two
calls that I've had, uh senior pastor of
First Presburg and IPC Memphis, um for
the last nine years or so. Uh and I
started teaching for RTS in 2011. Um but
but a big part of my kind of historical
project from listening in on the
conversations when I was a graduate
student at Westminster um through my
dissertation uh and then over the 13
years that I researched and wrote uh for
continuing church there there were there
were a number of stories uh about PCA
founding and PCA history that everyone
knew but no one had documented.
uh and uh we really didn't have a
credible kind of critical um
archivebased history that told the story
of if you will kind of a a southern
fundamentalism story of how the PCA came
to be. Most of the prominent historians
that had talked about the PCA or the PCA
origins like George Marsden for example
simply saw it either as uh its own
unique thing that wasn't tied to
northern fundamentalism at all or
northern evangelicalism at all or uh was
just kind of this weird u kind of u
native thing that just kind of came out
of nowhere. And so part of what I was
trying to do among many things I was
trying to do with the book uh was to try
to document those stories uh in
archivalbased research and try to show
that actually there's a lot of connect
points between the the southern
Presbyterian story that forms the PCA uh
and larger evangelicalism
um going back to prior to the
fundamentalist moderist controversy in
the north. Uh and really the there's
there's uh what happens in the 1920s and
what happens in the 20s and the 30s in
the south are in fact intimately
connected. Um the the southerners are
very much paying attention to what
happens to man. Um and they see a lot of
the same patterns happening in their own
church at the same time. So rather than
seeing the the northern story and the
southern story is two different stories,
they're really uh the same story played
out in two different locations or
context. That was one of the big things
I was trying to get at. So anyways, I
know we're going to get further into
that.
>> That's very helpful. What I was trying
to do.
>> Yeah. So maybe connected to that. Um how
like why do you think it's important for
the PCA right now to understand our
history?
I mean, you obviously felt like it was
important at the time you wrote it.
There was there's stories hadn't been
really documented and put together. Why
why do you think we might still need
your book today?
Yeah, I think for all the I've written
four different books um that are kind of
Presbyterian related two histories um
not counting church histories u because
I I wrote the history of first press
Jackson and first presber but the the
Dabney book and the four continuing
church book to me are really two parts
of the same story. Uh and then on being
Presbyterian and then this new little
book that just came out on
Presbyterianism that really talks about
beliefs, practice and stories and
Presbyterian identity. I I I really
think that we we desperately need to
think through what does it mean to be
Presbyterian? What does it mean to be
Presbyterian today? Uh and and and and
see our identity shaped not just by
beliefs and practices, but by the larger
stories that make these beliefs and
practices make sense. uh all too often,
especially on online discourse, but also
just in as seminarians come through,
they they think they know uh the stories
that make these beliefs and practices
make sense. Um or or they might sample a
particular slice of them. Um but but
they really don't know. Uh and so one of
the things that Ford continuing church
tries to do uh is to try to tell the
stories and show how um some of the some
of the beliefs and practices that we say
we value are actually much more
complicated
in terms of the living out of them uh
than than we might believe. most obvious
doctrine that is complicated in the
Presbyterian story is the spirituality
of the church or the the spiritual
mission of the church doctrine. Uh
[snorts] which was something that that
uh all the way back to the 30s southern
Presbyterian conservatives were were
agitated over as they saw the the the
liberal denominational leaders form
their permanent committee on social and
moral welfare, right?
>> And they railed against that committee
saying, "Well, no, we're for the
spiritual mission of the church." But um
they were sort of they you know they
they were constantly talking about
political social uh uh events uh in the
pages of the Southern Presbyterian
Journal which became the Presbyterian
Journal. Uh they were constantly
agitated about these things. So they
were articulating a conservative world
and life view that linked together
anti-integration, anti-entralization,
and anti-communism
uh in ways that then shaped the the
early beginnings at least of a certain
portion of the PCA. So yeah, trying to
pay attention to those stories and
understanding the the whole thing whole
uh will then help us make sense of the
beliefs and practices that we say we
value most.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It seems like our tradition
tends we like theology. We we like ideas
and so it's easy to kind of look at the
ideas and to kind of map out how we
understand these and lose sight of some
of the underlying cultural conditions uh
that are playing out in our history that
may be shaping how we understood those
ideas or even how those ideas are being
formed. Uh and so the if if you're cut
off from history, maybe it's harder to
know how to hold the things that we
believe or to understand the context of
the things that we we believe. Is that
fair or you think?
>> For sure. Oh, for sure. Yeah, very much
so.
>> Okay. Um, do you do you get the sense
that that most of the PCA elders that
you encounter today have a solid grasp
of our history as a denomination?
>> No, it's been one of the surprising
things uh I mean having written spent 13
years of my life on that book uh that uh
is actually sold relatively poorly
compared to say I'm being Presbyterian.
Um, I'm being Presbyterian's sold almost
30,000 copies um in 20 years, which is
pretty good. Um, and uh, four continued
church has sold about 5,000 copies in 10
years since it's come out. It came out
10 years ago this year. And um which is
a little surprising uh when you think
about seminarians uh people preparing
for ministry, elder training, all the
different venues where you would think
um [clears throat] uh an academically
credible but actually pretty readable
book might actually be informative to
understanding who in the world we are.
Um, which means then of course then that
means that the stories that we know are
just simply the stories that we tell
each other or or the stories that
represent our particular stream.
>> Um, you rather than you know I mean like
it or not. I mean that book is is rooted
in
exhaustive research through Presbyterian
Journal, Southern Presbyterian Journal,
Christian Outlook, Presbyterian Outlook,
the big the big Presbyterian magazines
and newspapers of that period as well as
a lot of time at Montre and at the PCA
historical center.
>> Well, and lots of correspondence right
between
>> right the correspondence yeah in the
archives. So um so I mean you know I
tried to tell the story of
>> you know as it happened. Now certainly I
have a perspective uh that uh I have a
story I want to tell. Um
>> but the the story that I wanted to tell
is of of these his these heroic yet
flawed leaders um who courageously
stepped out on behalf of the inspiration
of the Bible uh were willing to leave
their churches and even their church
properties if necessary in order to
stand for scripture. I mean that is the
overarching story. Yeah. uh for and and
that's true whether that's uh Kennedy
Smart uh whether that's Jim Kennedy, Jim
Bay, whether that's Morton Smith,
wherever you are uh on that kind of
ideological spectrum, they all were
agreed on that which then marks it out
as a kind of fundamentalism because to
me fundamentalism really if there is a
kind of fundamentalist doctrine that all
fundamentalists hold it's that the Bible
is the inspired, infallible and inherent
word of God. Yeah.
>> Um and they can all agree on that. The
the challenge comes when you when you
when you agree on that and you're
standing against a liberal
denominational leadership and then you
come out,
>> what what do you agree on now?
>> Right. Yeah. Right. Right.
>> And that that that becomes the challenge
from 1973 on.
>> Yeah. And maybe still part of what we're
facing today. Um I want to pick up on
that thread in a moment.
>> Um but uh I was wondering regarding your
book and the history of the PCA. I'm
unaware of any other book that tells a
distinct story about the PCA. You would
be more informed about that. Are there
other books on the history of the PCA
that that I should be reading?
>> Well, so Frank Smith was kind of the
pioneer. Frank Smith was uh like me, a
participant observant, was a PCA
teaching elder. His dad was a kind of a
founder of the PCA. Uh Frank is now an
RPCNA pastor in the Atlanta area. But
but he wrote his THM thesis that he then
expanded out uh his THM thesis at
Westminster that he expanded out into a
book uh on the history of the PCA and
that certainly has a perspective too. Uh
it would be educational to read that
book and my book side by side. Um
[snorts] Frank does a really nice job of
uh mining southern Presbyterian
Presbyterian Journal. Um doesn't doesn't
do much with archival research. doesn't
do much with kind of Presbyterian
minutes, session minutes, those kinds of
things. Um, but does a nice job at least
in that regard in terms of the the
public record uh with the Presbyterian
magazines. Um, the other thing that I I
think is really really valuable is Paul
Settle's 25th anniversary book uh and
Kennedy Smart's personal memoir I am
reminded. Um those are two uh kind of uh
uh colleagues on the steering committee
of 12 who who really led the beginning
of the PCA. Paul Settle was the the
first coordinator of what would become
our CDM uh committee on disciplehip
ministries and Kenny Smart was one of
the great leaders uh for evangelism and
mission in the PCA. Um, and their
stories are very similar. Even though
theologically they they
may not have uh they may have had
different sympathies, yet they were
bound together in a common vision for
what the PCA was going to be.
>> Namely, we're we're we're about mission.
Uh, yes, we're about reformed faith, but
but it's the reformed faith in order to
mission
>> uh and disciplehip. And uh and I think I
think they were just those two books
read together are I think really helpful
particularly at the 25 25th anniversary
mark uh to kind of hear their
reflections on those beginning days 25
years later. Super helpful.
>> Okay, that's great. I'll have to to
check those out. I did notice that you
have um a lot of endorsements from a a
broad swath of the PCA on here. I mean
you've you've got um Kevin D. Young uh
gave his blurb uh and I believe Harry
Reer does uh in here as well. Um I'm
trying to remember some of the other
guys. Uh Lian Duncan wrote the forward.
>> Um and then so I mean it it's you've got
a widespread group of PCA folks that
seem to say this is a reliable history
of the PCA. This is not a uh something
that's highly contested as far as I can
tell uh by anybody. So [gasps]
uh okay. Well, um, let's let's talk
about that founding vision of the PCA,
if you don't mind. Um, you know, how
would how would you describe that? What
were the founders, so to speak, trying
to build? Uh, or were there multiple
founding visions? I mean, you you said a
second ago they agreed on inherency.
That's largely what kind of kept them
together, but did they all kind of have
a different idea of what they were
building and then they got into it and
they're like, "Oh, wait a minute. We we
all want this to be very different." or
was there a generally broad uh consensus
on the the founding vision?
>> Yeah, I talk a little bit this about
this at the end of the book. Um
>> within 10 months uh Aken Taylor uh who
was certainly one of the leading
founders was the editor of the
Presbyterian Journal. Um he wrote for
Christianity Today uh magazine that
since the founding something along the
lines of since the founding of the PCA
in December 1973
um the the basically the guns have been
loaded, the battle lines have been
drawn. Um and and Taylor was
particularly concerned uh about what he
called the followers of of latter-day
followers of Calvin. Yeah. um who saw no
place for for conservative Presbyterians
to cooperate with Billy with Billy
Graham or with Bill Brightite in Campus
Crusade for Christ. Um one of the the
the key chapters in the book actually is
the Billy Graham chapter. Um because
it's pretty clear that in the 50s and
60s in the run-up to the formation of
the PCA that Billy Graham really was
kind of the bow ideal of of what uh the
Presbyterian conservative leaders wanted
uh in terms of uh bringing together a a
profound commitment to the inspiration,
fallibility, inherency, the authority of
scripture with a passion for evangelism
that would preserve American
civilization. So this this whole kind of
Christian nationalism thing, I mean
that, you know, the God and country has
been a thread throughout American
Christianity. There's some differences
about what's going on now uh in in
regards to Christian nationalism, but
there still was this sense from the
founders that um that the the evangelism
and mission was necessary in order to
preserve America. They very much had
America in their sights. Um and so in
that regard there, uh for those who've
read DG Hart's Lost Soul of American
Protestantism, um he he makes the point
that um you have kind of conservative
activists and liberal activists are
really they're they're different on
doctrine, but they're about the same
thing. They're activists. I mean, in a
real sense, the the founders of the PCA
were activists. Um they they they they
wanted mission. They wanted evangelism,
and they they they had a care for
American culture and civilization. Um
and so you know um that [clears throat]
that's the mainstream kind of founder
group. I mean even first press Jackson
um in the 50s and 60s uh they they
regularly supported Billy Graham both in
' 62 u when no excuse me in 52 when
Graham was in Jackson and then again
when Graham came uh in the 70s first
press Jackson supported the Graham
crusade. They had Bill Bright come and
speak in the 70s. Uh and so even a place
like First Press Jackson, uh which was
kind of the the mothership of the PCA, I
mean, they basically donated their
entire missions budget in the first
years of the PCA so that so that the PCA
could have a missions program. Um but
they were very much part of the kind of
the mainstream of American
evangelicalism. Uh John Reed Miller who
was the longtime pastor of First Pres
Jackson um uh Harold Oenay the the
president of the National Association of
Mogals did his wedding um they were they
were very very close friends uh and so
so the the mainstream u founders if you
will um very much wanted to be part of
American evangelicalism. uh they saw
themselves as kind of positioning the
PCA within this larger uh Billy Graham,
Nelson Bell, Christianity Today world.
Um but there was a there was a as Aken
Taylor noted there was a minority
position uh and that minority position
was really represented by Morton Smith.
>> Yeah. Um, and even in the runup to
December 4, 1973, some of the other
founders, um, like a, uh, Bill Hill, um,
who was the the head of Presbyterian
Evangelistic Fellowship, u, a noted
evangelist in the PCA, um, he would
write colleagues on the steering
committee expressing concern, uh, about
the the hypercalvinist group, he called
them. Um and so Morton from his position
uh at Reformed Theological Seminary um
was very influential with a young
generation
uh that uh saw themselves as wanting not
um this broadly evangelical denomination
but a thoroughly reformed one and they
adopted the moniker the TRS. Um and it
was and after the PCA forums in 73,
Morton will be instrumental in getting
Greg Bonson on the faculty of RTS in
order to promote this kind of what he
sees to be a thoroughly reformed um um
tradition uh which we now call theomy.
Um, but it was it was an attempt to try
to uh to to take scripture uh absolutely
seriously and apply it to American civil
life and and Christian ethics. Very
similar to Christian nationalism today.
Uh and and the whole Bonsson fiasco will
not only cost Bonson his job, but but it
will also cost Morton Smith his job.
Joey Pipo observed in a piece that he
wrote for Smith's 80th birthday um that
uh that Smith never got over the fact
that he stepped away from RTS. He felt
like the board had let him go.
>> It kind of maneuvered him out because
the board of RTS wisely was positioning
the seminary in the mainstream of what
the PCA was. even though it's a
non-denominational seminary, it's very
much been tied to the PCA uh and
represents that kind of broader um
vision uh of what it means to be
Presbyterian
uh so that it could serve not just the
PCA but other denominations as well,
Presbyterian denominations as well.
>> So, I'm going to I'm going to hone in on
that word broader because that's I think
just a a big area of controversy today,
the idea of being a broadly reformed
denomination. I think you use a number
of of words in in the last chapter, the
epilogue of your book, uh, like the PCA
was going to be an evangelical
denomination as opposed to, uh, what
what would that be contrasted with,
mainline or or liberal?
[snorts]
>> Yeah. So, I use the language of it was a
conservative, evangelical, mainline
denomination. Yeah. Uh, and each of
those words are intentional. So it's
conservative over against the
progressive liberal theologically
liberal denomination that they've left.
Um from 1942 on in the seminaries of the
PC US um the the infallibility of
scripture was regularly questioned and
undermined. Uh and so conservative
especially means uh that the Bible is
the inspired infallible inherent word of
God. And there's a chapter I think it's
uh chapter 8 that uh in the book that
talks about the different battles for
scripture right that the conservatives
wage. So conservative evangelical
>> that they're that they they're for the
gospel and for mission. Yeah.
>> So, one of the challenges in the PCUS in
the 60s was that the board of mission
world mission had moved away from uh an
evangelistic mission or a church
planting mission to a more
synchristianistic mission. Um similar to
what had happened in the northern
Presbyterian church. They they had made
the decision not to tell others that
Jesus is the only way to heaven but
rather to embrace the cultures that they
the missionaries found themselves.
Conservatives reprobated that. that
would lead to the the start of of ECO
the the uh the executive commission for
overseas evangelization
uh which was the international mission
out uh part of PEF uh and ECO would
actually be the predecessor it it would
eventually morph into MTW uh when the
PCA starts the commission ends and MTW
essentially takes over their work. So,
so evangelical is like a little bit
contrasted with more of a social focus
uh of the denomination. Okay.
>> Yeah. And then mainline is this kind of
cultural custodian concern uh for the
country um that that uh that you see all
the way through. Um, when the the
conservatives leave the PCUs, they don't
see themselves as they they see
themselves as a continuing church, not
of 1861,
let's have a a a racist church like the
the Presbyterian Church of the
Confederate States of America. They see
themselves as the continuing church of
this mainline body that stands as the
southern mainline body opposite of the
northern by then the United Presbyterian
Church, USA. Um and so so this
continuing church is this continuing
southern expression of the mainline
Presbyterian church. Um and they have
this sense of cultural custodianship
uh towards America and American culture.
That's why we need to evangelize. That's
why we need to church plant. We we care
for our country. And when they
eventually I mean that's why they their
founding names the National Presbyterian
Church.
>> Right. Yeah. I was going to ask if that
if national is a helpful word there
because they they saw the whole country
as something they wanted to be involved
in and caring for
>> right and they have a they have a
responsibility to it um both in terms of
evangelization but also in the
everyone's always observed the PCA's
always kind of punched above its weight
in kind of larger concerns you know CEO
of recoup ruling elder Ted Pres who's
the surgeon general of the United States
and all these different public figures
there has been this sense of kind of a
responsibility to the country that that
the best of the mainline tradition is
always represented and the PCA is at
least as founding saw itself that way
also.
>> Okay, that's really helpful. So the
going back to the word broad then um you
were saying that there was a [snorts]
sort of large consensus on this vision
that you're laying out. there was a the
presence of a a minority the the TRS the
hypercalvinist group um that that was
kind of influenced by Morton Smith but
that that wasn't like half the group
this was a pretty minor minor group
compared to the the consensus of most of
the founders.
>> Yeah. So the so I think it was Wayne
Sparkman who uh the director of the PC
historical center who documented he went
through the the the roster of who was at
the first general assembly uh and 18%
uh of the those teaching elders who were
at the first general assembly that
formed the PCA were RTS grads. Um so so
the the outer reach of Smith's influence
would have been with that 18%. Um I I I
don't expect that all 18% of the RTS
grads who were at the first general
assembly um would have agreed with
Smith's vision. In fact, I know that
that's not the case because I know
enough about the history early history
of the RTS to say that that's not the
case. But if you were just to kind of
guesstimate, you know, it's not more
than 20% at the founding. And it's
always this minority position. Yet on
the other hand, [clears throat] as
theonomy kind of royals the denomination
in the 70s and the 80s, the the the
founders who were kind of in control of
things, they they didn't drive the
theomy theonomist out. Now, you know,
from a church discipline standpoint in
terms of how theonomy was affecting
local churches, maybe that would have
made sense to drive the theomist out,
but they didn't. Um because again their
temp their vision was this large tent
vision um to and they they felt as
though if we can agree on the
inspiration infallibility and see of the
scripture and in good faith we're trying
to understand how this Bible relates to
our system of doctrine and how it
applies to the world then then we're
going to take all comers. Uh you know we
can't uh we can't be too picky right in
terms of who's going to be part of the
team.
>> Yeah. So
>> go ahead. Go ahead. finish with that
thought.
>> Yeah. So through all the default through
through that controversy and all the
different controversies that royal the
denomination um I mean really to the
present day that the default has been to
try to figure out how to create
boundaries and sidelines that are
inclusive not exclusive.
>> Yeah. So I said earlier there's kind of
these two narratives. A narrative like
decline versus a narrative of a fairly
consistent broadly reformed
denomination. Um, I've also heard people
say though that we've become maybe more
reformed in that the early founders
there was there was actually maybe more
breadth than we have today. A lot more
people that were just evangelical
um and and maybe not even that
Calvinistic or maybe slightly more
charismatic or uh maybe just not as
theological in general and and then on
the whole our ministers and elders
broadly are maybe more reformed. Would
you agree with that or do you think
that's
>> Yeah, for sure. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean
one of the first arguments that we have
almost immediately after the PCA forms
is over charismatic gifts. Um because
you know, think back 1973, 1974, Jesus
Movement, Crusade,
um Explo 72 in Dallas, this huge crusade
that Billy Graham has. The the the the
main serious evangelicals are young
Jesus people, uh who are kind of
charismatic, twinged. And so they
they're coming into the PCA to help form
the PCA. Uh and we're having then to
write this amazing pastoral letter with
at the third, you know, at the second
general assembly essentially um to try
to say, okay, we're so glad you're here.
Um but but how do we think about
spiritual gifts and how do especially
these charismatic sign gifts? You can
pray in your private prayer language,
but um it's not revelatory. Uh don't go
around don't go in your church service
and start spouting off. Um, and so they
they try to exercise their wisdom
because, hey, these folks who showed up
at the first PCA parties, they're not
that reformed. Um, you know, and you
think back, I mean, RTS was a relatively
small school in Jackson, Mississippi.
You know, Covenant Seminary barely had
100 students. Westminster wasn't that
large. I mean, you fast forward now 50
years past the founding, RTS is one of
the largest theological seminaries in
the country. uh Covenant in the 2010s uh
in the late as 2010s when I was uh
academic dean there. Um we were one of
the 20 largest seminaries in the
country. Westminister produces a number
of M divi Master of Divinity graduates.
So you just think about how the the
training that people have gotten and
just the numbers. Um we're far more
reformed now uh than we were at the
founding. There's no question about
that.
>> Well, what about along the way though? I
mean, there's been a number of
controversies,
study reports. Um, have we been
loosening things all along the way or
have we been largely putting kind of
staking off where the boundaries have
generally been and how do we keep people
together? I mean, how would you
describe, you know, the various
controversies we've had?
>> Yeah. So at at um in the last chapter of
on being Presbyterian uh I talk about I
think I talk about six different
controversies
uh that from the founding to 2003 which
is basically when I finished the book I
that came out in ' 05 or '06. Um,
[snorts] so you know, charismatic gifts,
creation days, confessional
subscription,
um, I forget the other ones. Theonomy,
um, you know, the the default has has
been to try to figure out, okay, here
are the sidelines and the guard rails.
If you're inside those sidelines and
guard rails, you're okay. Uh, if you're
outside, we've got issues. I mean, the
creation day report, I think, is a great
example of that. you know the this is
these are the sinqanon
um that you have to affirm when it comes
to uh chapter four of the west
confession of faith on creation uh and
then when we think about in the space of
six days these are the acceptable
positions but you better be able to
explain yourself especially if you
divert from calendar day uh and um
beyond that let's let's let's have some
peace and really from 2003 on
>> I mean that document men has served us
extremely well uh as we've examined
hundreds and hundreds and hundreds of
men both teaching elders and ruling
elders who've come through. Yeah.
>> Um so that yeah that our default has
been to try to find um here you know
we're going to set boundaries um because
we believe the confession in scripture
does as well but but not narrow
boundaries that are exclusive but as
inclusive as possible within a
commitment to the inherency of scripture
uh and the system of doctrine that's
summarized for us in the standards.
>> Yeah.
Okay. Vering a little bit into the issue
of subscription. you I think you got
ordained in the same year that we
ratified good faith subscription uh
2003.
>> In your understanding, was that a new
position of the PCA that that was being
ratified or was that essentially putting
into our documents largely how things
were operating up until that point?
>> Yeah. So, yeah, 2003 Charlotte, 2004
Pittsburgh is when we finished all that
up at General Assembly. Um and uh yeah,
so one of the so I I'm just finishing
teaching American Presbyterianism for
RTS this semester. One of the things
we've charted through the the semester
is from 1729 on
from the adopting act on uh American
Presbyterians regardless of the stripe
have been arguing over what does it mean
to subscribe to this document? Um it's
it's clear to me at least although uh
the the strict subscription folks
through through 300 years have argued
otherwise. Pretty clear to me that in
the adopting act itself there was an
allow for scruples or for some measure
of difference with the standards. Um but
but be that as it may, as you kind of
chart that history forward, one of the
things that's never really defined is
what are the essential and necessary
doctrines or what are the fundamentals
of the system of doctrine from 1929 on.
>> Um and so u there will be attempts in
Presbyterian history to try to define
them um those essential and necessary
doctrines. Um actually that that creates
its own sets of problems. um defining
certain doctrines as essent essential
and necessary means that others are not
as uh essential or necessary um kind of
logically. Um but be that as it may,
they're they're never defined. Um so
what happens uh when the PCA forms and
we're arguing over subscription
especially after joining and receiving
in 1982 where you have uh the ar the
reformed Presbyterian Church Evangelical
Senate uh a group of churches
representing about 30,000 communicate
members that join and receive. They come
into the PCA and we receive them. They
have a different history, a different
tradition, different fights, different
contexts. when they come in from 82
until uh 2003, we basically argue over
what does subscription mean?
[clears throat]
Uh and and what good faith subscription
was meant to do uh was like you say
ratify what we have been doing but also
put it in the hands of the local court
to determine what are the essential and
necessary doctrines
subject to some some means of appeal.
Now the solution that we came up with uh
that that I think all of us could
foresee back in 2003 2004 of making RPR
that court of appeals through which the
general assembly hears about different
things not the best solution. Um
probably needed to think of a better
solution than the one we ended up with.
But be that as it may, it you know for
20ome years now we've been doing this
and you know we've been able to regulate
uh what are essential and necessary
doctrines. Um there have been cases uh
out of which complaints have been
brought um that have gone to the SJC
over different differences that were
allowed. Fair enough. uh that's
absolutely appropriate um for for
presbitors to raise questions about um
differences that are allowed through the
through the complaint process that our
book affords. Um but but but it's really
an attempt to to push down to the lowest
court that has the most oversight over
teaching elders and and the churches
that are received by the presbyteries to
to make those determinations
uh about what are essential and
necessary. Yeah. [clears throat]
So, it having just served on RPR in the
last several years, um this question of
knowing our history kind of came up.
There was several exceptions that were
flagged that some of the guys in the
room had to say, "Guys, we've we've been
granting these exceptions for years. Um
this has gone to the general assembly
multiple times in the past 15 years.
It's been allowed. I don't know why
we're flagging it this time." And and
most of the guys in the room just didn't
know that. Um, and then then there was
the issue of a lot of them didn't seem
to care that that was the case. So
that's another question. But at least
from a a history standpoint, it seems
like uh a lot of folks today don't
understand what our practice of
subscription has been. What are a lot of
the exceptions that have kind of been
seen as within the bounds? And so
they're they're they're looking at
things now and saying this looks like
liberalism. Uh, you know, this looks
like we're sliding. So from your view as
a historian, I mean, would you say the
PCA has has been sliding into liberalism
the last five decades? We we've been
kind of slowly declining back to where
we came from.
>> Well, so I had an elder at my previous
church who um was always saying this. We
were sliding into liberalism. Uh and um
I remember being at a general assembly
where we argued over the allowability of
p of communion. Uh we argued over uh
image of Jesus on a worship bulletin for
a presbyter. Uh and we argued over uh
some other doctrinal matter. And like if
you know anything about the history of
American religion or even just the
current landscape of American religion,
those are not arguments that liberal
denominations have. Um those are kind of
technical nicities and refinements
within the reformed tradition uh that um
that that that don't touch on liberalism
at all but really touch on particular
ways in which to hold the system of
doctrine.
>> Yeah.
>> Um so no I mean one of the I actually
was literally talking about this last
week in class. One of the liberal
theological liberalism is a is a
historically defined term and movement.
Uh it has its roots back all the way
back to Fred Schlamacher the father of
German theological liberalism gets
mediated to America by Horus Bushnell
and others. It it has its own
provenence. Um but fundamental to it is
that creeds are only the highest wisdom
of any given moment in time. um they're
they are second order reflections on
first order religious experience and so
we should expect creeds to change um and
um
uh and you know Jonathan Edwards
believed in the hory doctrine of hell
David swing said but uh 19th century
Presbyterian ministry but no
Presbyterian believes that today he says
well well how could he say that was
because creeds are simply the highest
reflection of religious experience at a
given moment in time there is no one in
the PCA who says that like there is
literally no one who says that. Uh we're
one of the largest denominations in the
country uh that requires its officers to
s to take a vow that they affirm that
the Bible is the inherent word of God.
>> The only denomination that's larger than
us that requires that of their pastors
is the Lutheran Church of Missouri
Senate. Um Southern [snorts] Baptists
can't require that because of course
Southern Baptist ordination is tied to
the local church. And so I mean there we
have issues no doubt uh but but in terms
of fundamental attitude towards
scripture, fundamental attitude towards
creeds, we are we are just definitely we
are not there is no one here that's a
theological liberal. Um so yeah I it's
it's always been the concern though. uh
when Morton Smith was the moderator u in
2000, he gives his moderator's address
in 2001 at Dallas. Uh and he warned in
2001 uh of the encroaching liberalism in
the PCA and that the PCA will split uh
within his lifetime. Of course, Dr.
Smith is with the Lord. We're still
here. But that's always been the
expectation and fear, right, is that
liberalism will come in, denominations
inevitably decline, uh, and we will
split and divide at some point in time.
Um, the the fact of the matter is is
that both on the far the far left and
far right, if I can use those terms,
there is no far left and far right in
the PCA, but on our ends, those folks
leave for other places um because they
know this is what the PCA is. um you
know, and they want something that's
more narrow or more broad than what we
are, fair enough. Um but the PCA's had a
pretty consistent place uh within um
kind of the American evangelical
landscape. And I think it's one of the
reasons why um by God's mercy, we're one
of the few denominations that's still
growing today. Yeah. um is because
because we stand for the the inherency
of scripture and we stand for a a
winsome approach to the reformed faith
summarized in the the Westminster
standards and we're also for mission and
we want to be obedient to the great
commission. We have the largest
missionary Anglo-American missionary
force in the world. We have the largest
reformed campus ministry in the world.
Uh I mean over you know 30 church
planning network. I mean we got these
all these amazing things. Um because
we're we want to be obedient to the
great commission. So yeah, that's that's
who we are and that's that's what we've
been. [clears throat]
>> You you talked about that issue of uh
division, the fear of division um going
back all the way to the beginning too.
Uh that some of the founders saw the OPC
and the way that it started and then
split very quickly
>> and intentionally said we do not want to
be a denomination that fights over these
little debates within the reform system
uh and fractures like that. I mean that
that's that that was a different concern
about splitting and then you know like
you said later on people have said we're
going to split maybe because of
liberalism but do you think there needs
to be more of a focus and and a sort of
attentiveness to trying to cultivate a
holding together of the PCA in in the
increased polarization we're seeing
right now. Lots of talk about how
there's a split, lots of talk about how
we're moving towards liberalism. Is that
do you think that's healthy? Do we need
to kind of remember who we've been and
and try to figure out how we can hold
together or do you think this is a a
kind of a different moment requiring
different approaches?
>> Yeah. I So I still believe uh like Tim
Keller said so many years ago, the PCA
is the best mess out there. Um and but
but unity is something that has to be
cultivated. It can't be assumed. Uh and
part of the way we cultivate that is in
good faith. we work in our local
context. um you know I if if the
different churches are participating in
presbyter um not just in terms of
showing up to take votes but doing the
hard work of committees and having to
work together then you suddenly you get
to know guys who may not be your you
know kind of your theological
stripe um but you see like wow he's had
an amazing faithful ministry for 40 plus
years in this particular place and wow I
mean we may not be in the same spot
exactly but I can't help but respect
this brother. Uh or, you know, wow,
he's, you know, I may not phrase it just
the way he does, but the fact he cares
about mission and church planting and
and evangelization and reaching out to
those who are so different from us, um,
I wouldn't do it exactly the same way,
but wow, I so appreciate him. the more
we can do ministry together and get to
know each other at the presbyter level
rather than seeing presbyter as a
necessary evil um the the more we can
actually build the different senus of
trust that will hold us together. Um I
so my last place in Hattisburg,
Mississippi, we we had a ministry called
Hope for Hattisburg that was a
partnership with Ebenezer Missionary
Baptist Church, which is a historically
black church uh on the east side of our
town um in a section of town that the
locals referred to as the Gula. Uh and
uh their pastor, Carlos Wilson, was just
an amazing man. and kind of post
Katrina, we worked together, developed
this organization to rebuild houses,
rebuild places, rebuild persons. So, we
had a a building outreach, we worked at
lo in a local school together, and we
also had a health outreach. And uh you
know, and then Carlos and I had lunch uh
with other pastors uh at least once a
quarter.
Then building was really really
important. um in 2012 and 2016 as
different local elections happened
especially as well as the national
elections um and to to see the different
sides react in different ways about what
was happening either locally or
nationally and to be able to say to my
folks or for him to be able to say to
his folks no wait you know we can't
think that about our friends like I know
Carlos we've worshiped with them we've
built houses together like no we can't
or like no no no you can't talk about
Sean that way. Um, we know that,
brother. Uh, and so the the more we do
stuff together and and learn to trust
each other at the local area, the the
the better it's going to be. Now, having
said that, we still have to act well,
you know, and I mean publicly. Uh, and
one of the challenging things of our
very very hyperonline moment.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, is that not everyone is is is a good
actor online. Uh, and that that arose
trust. Uh and so
>> yeah, that seems to be a huge factor. I
think another factor related to the
first point you were making there is
that it seems like the PCA has had for
much of its history sort [snorts] of
churchmen that maybe came at things from
different perspectives but were had like
public friendships and public
conversations. Even at the founding, uh
people maybe saw things different than
Morton Smith, but they were writing to
him and they talked and they worked
together. Uh and he was clerk. Yeah.
Right. Um and and of course you had that
with uh Tim Keller and Ligan Duncan u
very public in their friendship but also
in their disagreements and uh the way
they dialogue was really helpful. Is do
you think we're missing that right now
that we don't quite have the same
churchmen who are kind of publicly known
throughout the PCA and and sort of have
a public friendship that allows them to
model some of that friendship and
charity that we need? [snorts]
>> Yeah. I think I just in the the forest
of circumstances has played out over the
last I don't know 10 15 years um we've
kind of cordoned off into our groups um
and I'm saying this as executive board
member of AMR um but we've cordoned off
in our groups whereas what you've
described are guys from different sides
or groups willing to talk together and
meet together and work together and say
this guy's my brother um we agree on 90,
you know, 5%. Um, you know, I never
forget at the seminar that Lig and Tim
did where they said like they actually
put their hands on top of each other. We
agreed this much like we're like
completely agreed except for a few like
details on the outside, right? Um, you
know, to have uh the the big steeple
pastors uh across the kind of the
ideological places within this little
narrow band of the BCA. if if we were
all to kind of say, "Hey, you know, we
really actually agree on like 99%." You
know, we you know, there's some
different emphases or different
perspectives or whatever or what we're
willing to tolerate versus other things,
whatever. Um but like we're actually
friends, like we actually get along. We
actually work together. Um and to kind
of refrain from saying, "Oh, I disagree
with him. He's a progressive." Or, "Oh,
I disagree with him. He's a
fundamentalist." like, you know, to be
actually to to speak well of one another
publicly. I think that would be hugely
important. Um, I do think it's I mean,
yes, it's incumbent on all, you know,
2,000 senior pastors of the 2,000
churches, the 5,000 teaching elders or
how many ever, but I do think the larger
selectors
have to model that. And so,
>> which is what Le and Tim did, right? I
mean,
>> yeah, for sure. Well, what else should I
have asked you when it comes to the
history of the PCA that I've failed to
ask you about? Because I think this has
been a really helpful kind of course
crash course on our history and who we
who we are.
>> Yeah. I think I think the only other
thing I would reflect on out of the for
continuing church piece is that um you
know because of the the post 2016 swing
uh away from racial reconciliation
uh and you know perhaps exacerbated by
2020 and all that happened around George
Floyd. Um there's there's this this
renewed amnesia kind of about what
happened in the 50s and the 60s. Um, we
can't do that. Uh, we just can't. Um,
the PCA 2018 racial and ethnic
reconciliation report was adopted
unanimously. Uh, and even though that
report, which I helped to write, was was
forgotten in the in the the tsunami that
was Revoice. Um, I I I think the the
intention and the vision of what we did
in 0405
and 16 and 18, we can't forget that. Um
there's there's this new mood to try to
somehow say that noting racial
difference um as part of the PCA is
somehow bad. Um but you can only say
that from a majority culture position
and a a willful ignorance of our
history.
Uh, and so, um, it's it's it's someone
who who's who's who spent a lot of time
thinking about the history of black
Presbyterianism and more the need for
our black brothers and sisters, our
brown brothers and sisters to be with
us, uh, to speak into the system, to
speak truth to the system, uh, and to be
able to say to us, no, this is the
faithful way. Uh, I we need that more
now than ever. I'll never forget being
on a panel with Carl Ellis back in 2015,
I think. Uh, and one of the points that
Carl made that I thought was really,
really important was there's coming a
day in America where all Christians will
experience significant persecution,
opposition. And one of the gifts that
the black church has for us is they've
known what that persecution opposition
has been their entire existence. And so
if if if the white brothers and sisters
among us can humble ourselves to to
value the gifts that our black brothers
and sisters can give in that respect and
many other respects besides we will be
so much richer because of that. And so
that to me I just I I you know we've had
a lot of crazy discussions here over the
last year about race um that I think
ignores the the big one of the big
lessons out of for continuing church.
Uh, and I would hate for us um to
continue to to live with that kind of
amnesia because like it or not, our our
country is racially and culturally
diverse and if we're going to reach our
country for the gospel, we have to pay
attention to these things. We cannot
ignore them.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
Well, that's a very uh helpful note uh
to end on. Sean, thank you for um
everything you've shared with us today
and uh I do hope it helps us get uh more
acquainted with our history so that we
can move forward together um in a way
that is effective uh for like you said
planting churches, reaching our
neighbors. So, thanks for your time and
uh thank you everyone who's uh listened
to this or watched this today. Um we're
hoping to put out a few more
>> [music]
>> uh discussions like this that um just
help the PCA know who we are and think
about where [music] we're going
together. So, thanks everyone.
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
[music]